<Publish>
  <!-- Id is not required for publishing the mod for the first time. Fill it after PDX assigns one. -->
  <ModId Value="148570" />
  <DisplayName Value="Articulated Buses" />
  <ShortDescription Value="Enables articulated (bendy) bus assets by spawning and driving a linked rear trailer section for compatible bus prefabs." />
  <LongDescription>## About this mod
The base game currently has no built-in support for **articulated buses**. This mod provides a **temporary workaround** for this functionality (it does not contain any assets).
You do not need to configure anything. Just subscribe to any articulated bus asset using this mod, that's it.

## How-to for creators
This mod is designed to be as update-safe as possible if native articulated-bus support is added later.

- No custom data is stored in prefabs or save games.
- Assets and saves remain usable without the mod.
- The mod works mainly on a cosmetic/rendering level.
- It applies its logic to any **bus-type car prefab** with a **Car Tractor** component.

### What this mod does
- Extends the game's existing car/truck trailer logic to buses.
- Enables trailers for public-transport bus prefabs with a **Car Tractor** component.
- Uses parts of the train/tram connection logic for walkways and bellows.
- Supports multiple **Vehicle Connection** bones for smoother accordion-style bending.

### 1. Preface
Use two separate models and prefabs **Bus front** and **Trailer**
Import both as vanilla-compatible `.fbx` files with axis orientation: **-Z Forward, Y Up**.

### 2. Bone setup and rigging
Rig the bending vertices to one or more **Vehicle Connection** bones.

For a simple joint:
- Use one **Vehicle Connection** bone.
- This is fully sufficient and works similarly to trains and trams.
- Recommended for LOD1 and LOD2.

For smoother accordion bending:
- Use a parented chain of connection bones.
- Run the chain from the body toward the gap.
- Set every connection bone to **Vehicle Connection** in the editor.

Chain example: root bone -&gt; connection bone -&gt; connection bone -&gt; ... -&gt; final connection bone

Additional setup notes:
- The final connection bone sits at the gap between both sections. It acts as the actual connection point.
- The mod distributes the bend across the chain. More bones create smoother bending.
- All bones must be oriented -Z Forward (as the prefab models).

### 3. Front section: main bus
Import the front section like a normal bus as **Car Prefab**.
Add a **Car Tractor** component and set:
- **Fixed Trailer**: your trailer asset
- **Trailer Type**: **Fixed**

### 4. Rear section: trailer
Import the rear section as a **Car Trailer Prefab** and set:
- **Trailer Type**: **Fixed**
- **Fixed Tractor**: leave empty

**Do not** link the trailer back to the front manually (a two-way prefab link crashes the game when a save is loaded).
**Do not** try to reuse trailer prefabs for multiple bus fronts. Trailers should be unique per front section (won't break anything, but leads to only one bus with a working trailer due to game limitations). Incorrect setups are logged with both front prefab names in `.../Cities Skylines II/Logs/TINB.ArticulatedBuses.session.log`.

### 5. Color properties
To make the trailer follow the front section's livery and transport-line color add a **Color Properties** component to the trailer. Configure it like the bus front. Set it to "Brand".
The mod then matches trailer color, per-vehicle shade and repaint changes made to the front section automatically.

### Bonus: Asset Icon Creator support
When using [Asset Icon Creator by TDW](https://mods.paradoxplaza.com/mods/105288/Windows), the mod automatically spawns trailers for snapshots. This allows icons to show the full articulated bus (in rare cases this may not work - then just reload the asset in the editor and try again).

## Disclaimer
* This mod is a **temporary solution**. Once the game adds native articulated-bus support, this mod will become obsolete and **deprecated**.
* **Removing this mod will not break save games.** The mod stores no custom save data and only uses vanilla game data.
* Not required, but recommended before removal:
	&gt; 1. Load your save game.
	&gt; 2. Open the mod options.
	&gt; 3. Run the pre-removal clean-up.
	&gt; 4. Save the clean save game.
	&gt; 5. Remove the mod.

Final note: this mod was created with some help from coding agents.</LongDescription>
  <Thumbnail Value="Properties/Thumbnail.png" />
  <ForumLink Value="https://forum.paradoxplaza.com/forum/threads/articulated-buses-mod.1930913/" />
  <ModVersion Value="1.0.5" />
  <GameVersion Value="1.6.*" />
  <ChangeLog># v1.0.5
- Optimisation: partly refactor of class structure for efficiency and optimisation
- Improved: session logging
- Improved: code documentation (converted to xml commenting standard)

# v1.0.4
- Added: Mod pre-removal cleanup to remove all articulated buses in one click, a simple precaution for a fully clean save before removing the mod.
- Added: optional diagnostic-logging, to make reporting a bug easier.
- Improved: general stability and memory usage, especially during long play sessions.

# v1.0.3
- Fix: resolved a random crash to desktop that could happen during normal play (most often while buses were being reassigned between lines, or returning to the depot).
- Fix: when a bus is moved to a different line, its trailer now correctly takes on the new line's color instead of keeping the old one.

# v1.0.2
- Fix: upgrading or extending a bus depot no longer crashes to desktop when articulated buses are stationed there (a crash that could occur in 1.0.1).
- Fix: articulated buses now garage inside the depot instead of surface-parking, so the trailer no longer overhangs and blocks the depot driveway.

# v1.0.1
- Fix: parked articulated buses are now un-spawning, so they no longer block the depot driveway or hold up other buses. Caveat: no articulated bus can be observed parked, but that's the trade-off.

# v1.0.0
Initial release.</ChangeLog>
  <Tag Value="Code Mod" />
  <AccessLevel Value="Public" />
</Publish>