<Publish>
  <!-- Id is not required for publishing the mod for the first time. Fill it after PDX assigns one. -->
  <ModId Value="148570" />
  <DisplayName Value="Articulated Buses" />
  <ShortDescription Value="Enables articulated (bendy) bus assets by spawning and driving a linked rear trailer section for compatible bus prefabs." />
  <LongDescription>
## About this mod

The base game has no built-in support for **articulated (bendy) buses** (yet). This mod is a **temporary workaround** that fills that gap.

You don't need to configure anything to *use* an articulated bus asset that already ships set up for this mod — just subscribe to the asset, subscribe to this mod (if not automatically done).

## How-to for creators

First of all: this mod is designed to be as update-safe regarding a possible future implementaion of actual mechanics in the base game by the game devs, as possible.
That means, it does not save anything in the prefabs / saves that would break a) either assets relying on the mod nor b) save-games.
The mod works at the rather cosmetic /render level. It applies its render-logic on top any car prefab defined as bus, that carries a car tractor component.


**What this mod does**
It relies on already existing vanilla mechanics of the game and expands the code used for trucks/trailers towards buses (otherwise currently the game ignores trailers attached to bus, i.e. public transport type bus car prefabs with car tractor components).
To allow for proper walkways/bellows some of the train/tram mechanics are applied on top - plus additional support for multiple vehicle connection bones to allow for "accordion-like" inter-section bending.

**1. Front section — the main bus**
- Import your main bus front just like any other bus. Add the **Car Tractor** component to attach the back as trailer. In the settings, set the **Fixed Trailer** to your rear trailer asset and set the **Trailer Type** to **Fixed**.

**2. Rear section — the trailer**
- Import as **Car Trailer Prefab** and set its **Trailer Type** to **Fixed**.
- **Important**: Leave its *Fixed Tractor* field empty — do *not* link it back to the front. Linking both directions in the saved asset makes the game crash when a save is loaded. The mod re-creates that back-link automatically while it's running, so you never set it by hand.

**3. Vehicle connection / bone setup**
- It works like a train/tram coupling. For the bending joint, this mod borrows the game's existing **train/tram vehicle-connection** logic: rig the vertices to be transformed as **Vehicle Connection** bone(s).
- Unlike trains/trams, you can use several connection bones for a smooth accordion. Build a *chain* of connection bones as a parent hierarchy running from the body toward the gap:

`root bone → first connection bone → second connection bone → … → last bone (the connection point)`

Each connection bone is parented to the previous one. The **last bone sits at the gap** where it meets the other section and acts as the actual connection point. In the editor select **Vehicle Connection** for all connection bones. The mod spreads the bend evenly across the chain, so more bones = smoother connection bending.
- **Note:** A single connection bone is absolutely sufficient, bone hierarchy chains are optional — one Vehicle Connection bone gives a fully working articulated joint just as for trains and trams. Especially for LOD1 and LOD2 a single bone will be sufficient.


**4. Colour properties**
- To make the trailer follow the front's livery and the transport-line colour, add a Color Properties component to the trailer as well and configure it the same way as for the bus front. The mod then matches the trailer's colours and per-vehicle shade to the front automatically, and follows any repaint a user makes on the bus front (in case a user selects a custom colour on the trailer only, the front will not follow).
- If a trailer has no Color Properties component or is not set to "Brand" the trailer will just carry its own colours.

**Bonus: Asset Icon Creator support**
In case you should be using the great [Asset Icon Creator by TDW](https://mods.paradoxplaza.com/mods/105288/Windows): the mod hooks into the snapshot tool and automatically spawns trailers for the shot.
This way you can easily create a proper icon for the entire bus front with trailer combination.

## Disclaimer

This mod is a **temporary solution**. Articulated buses are not yet a base-game feature, and this mod works around that gap. Once the game adds native articulated-bus support, this mod will become obsolete and **deprecated**.

**Removing this mod will not break your save games.** The mod stores no custom save data — it only uses vanilla game data — so a save made with the mod will load fine without it.

What changes when the mod is removed: any articulated bus in your city will remain intact - except for the bending. New buses will not spawn a trailer. The **front bus asset keeps working** as an ordinary single-section bus — it stays on its line, carries passengers, and behaves normally.

-- Final note: this mod was created with some help of coding-agents
</LongDescription>
  <Thumbnail Value="Properties/Thumbnail.png" />
  <ForumLink Value="https://forum.paradoxplaza.com/forum/threads/articulated-buses-mod.1930913/" />
  <ModVersion Value="1.0.3" />
  <GameVersion Value="1.6.*" />
  <ChangeLog># v1.0.3
- Fix: resolved a random crash to desktop that could happen during normal play (most often while buses were being reassigned between lines, or returning to the depot).
- Fix: when a bus is moved to a different line, its trailer now correctly takes on the new line's colour instead of keeping the old one.

# v1.0.2
- Fix: upgrading or extending a bus depot no longer crashes to desktop when articulated buses are stationed there (a crash that could occur in 1.0.1).
- Fix: articulated buses now garage inside the depot instead of surface-parking, so the trailer no longer overhangs and blocks the depot driveway.

# v1.0.1
- Fix: parked articulated buses are now un-spawning, so they no longer block the depot driveway or hold up other buses. Caveat: no articulated bus can be observed parked, but that's the trade-off.

# v1.0.0
Initial release.

- Articulated (bendy) bus support: spawns and drives a linked rear trailer for compatible bus assets.
- Smooth deforming bellows via a rigid Vehicle Connection bone chain (one bone, or several for a finer accordion).
- Trailer livery and transport-line colour kept in sync with the front; custom repaints follow.
- Trailer boarding/alighting doors are used in game.
- Asset Icon Creator support: the trailer is included in the captured icon.
- No custom save data: removing the mod is safe — the trailer disappears and the bus front keeps working.</ChangeLog>
  <Tag Value="Code Mod" />
  <AccessLevel Value="Public" />
</Publish>
